{"tossups": [{"question": "Description acceptable. According to the original account of this event, it ended with an \u201cact of heroism\u201d worth \u201cmore than a thousand [things], though blossomed with silver.\u201d The target of this event was attacked after the perpetrator \u201camused himself hacking his mother\u2019s pea sticks.\u201d This event took place after its perpetrator was, at the age of six, \u201cmade the wealthy master of a hatchet,\u201d according to an 1800 biography. For ten points, name this legend, told as a fable by Parson Weems, in which a six-year-old future American President admitted he \u201ccould not tell a lie\u201d and confessed to arboreal vandalism.", "answer": "George<b> Washington cutting down a cherry tree</b> (accept additional information; prompt on partial answers; prompt on descriptions of \u201cGeorge Washington not being able to tell a lie\u201d or similar response by asking the player \u201ccould not tell a lie about what?\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this dynasty, Chancellor Wang Anshi implemented the \u201cNew Policies,\u201d which were criticized by poet Su Shi, leading to Shi\u2019s eventual exile. Mongke Khan died while besieging this dynasty at the Battle of Diaoyu Fortress in Chongqing. This dynasty\u2019s rulers resolved border conflicts with the Liao dynasty, which was later overthrown in a combined effort by this dynasty and the Jurchen people. This dynasty is split into distinct \u201cNorthern\u201d and \u201cSouthern\u201d periods due to the loss of northern China to the Jin Dynasty in 1127. The first use of gunpowder came during, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty that was conquered by the Mongols in 1279?", "answer": "<b> Song</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This event\u2019s trophy, the Woodlawn Vase, was buried in Kentucky for protection during the Civil War. Survivor\u2019s record margin of victory in this event in 1873 was not surpassed until 2004 by Smarty Jones. In 1973, employees of<em> Daily Racing Form</em> confirmed that Secretariat set a speed record of 1 minutes 53 seconds at this event, whose winner is draped in faux-Black-Eyed Susans. Pimlico Race Course annually hosts this event in Maryland three weeks before the Belmont Stakes. For ten points, name this second race of the Triple Crown.", "answer": "<b> Preakness</b> Stakes (do not accept or prompt on Triple Crown)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In January 2017, this state prevented a passenger train painted in red, blue, and white from reaching the town of Mitrovica [mee-troh-veet-zah]. This state normalized relations with its northern neighbor as part of the 2013 Brussels Agreement. This state\u2019s former Prime Minister, Ramush Haradinaj, was arrested by the French government in 2017. In 2008, this territory declared its independence, which was recognized by the United States but not Russia. For ten points, name this breakaway Muslim republic of Serbia whose capital is Pristina [prish-teen-ah].", "answer": "<b> Kosovo</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This politician used his weekly radio show,<em> Talk to the People</em>, to read the Sunday comics to listeners during a newspaper deliveryman\u2019s strike. This politician targeted Frank Costello by ordering the dumping of thousands of slot machines into the ocean. While in the House of Representatives, he co-sponsored a legislation that protected collective bargaining rights by outlawing \u201cyellow dog\u201d contracts. For ten points, identify this 20th century mayor of New York City who names an airport in Queens.", "answer": "Fiorello<b> La Guardia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While being led to his execution, this man told fellow inmate Payne Best \u201cThis is the end; for me, the beginning of life.\u201d This man, who distinguished between \u201ccheap\u201d and \u201ccostly\u201d types of grace in<em> The Cost</em> <em>of Discipleship</em>, was killed after being exposed as a co-planner of the July 20th Plot while he worked as an<em> Abwehr</em> agent. This man worked with Karl Barth to help found the Confessing Church, which opposed the Protestant unification attempts of the Nazis. For ten points, name this Lutheran pastor and dissident.", "answer": "Dietrich<b> Bonhoeffer</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s Orange Walk District is home to the ancient city of Lamanai, and a logger discovered Caracol here while searching for mahogany trees. European settlers here known as Baymen fought the battle of St. George\u2019s Caye. This country relocated its capital inland in response to 1961\u2019s Hurricane Hattie, and was known as British Honduras until 1973. Belmopan is the capital of, for ten points, what Central American country that, like neighboring Mexico and Guatemala, is home to a number of Mayan ruins?", "answer": "<b> Belize</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this activist who J. Edgar Hoover wiretapped and encouraged to commit suicide with the aforementioned letter.", "answer": "Dr. Martin Luther<b> King</b> Jr.", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "At the first Council of Nicaea, this man legendarily struck Arius across the face. Every May 9, this man\u2019s tomb in Bari is harvested for its holy manna, a clear oil. This saint, nicknamed \u201cthe wonderworker,\u201dgave a poor man three gold balls as dowries for his daughters while this man served as the Bishop of Myra. At the beginning of Advent, this saint\u2019s feast day commemorates his habit of putting coins in children\u2019s shoes and giving gifts. For ten points, name this patron saint of children, immortalized as Santa Claus.", "answer": "Saint<b> Nicholas</b> (accept<b> Nikolaos</b> of Myra; accept<b> Santa Claus</b> or<b> Sinterklaus</b> before\u201cSanta Claus\u201d is read) Page 2", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Bloody killings along a street in this country\u2019s capital led that street to be called \u201cMurder Mile.\u201d The Treaty of Guarantee established the independence of this country, which was led by a man who attempted to overturn ethnic restrictions imposed on governmental positions in the London and Z\u00a8urich Agreements. In 1974, Nikos Sampson overthrew Archbishop Makarios III in this country, whose incorporation with Greece was an example of<em> enosis</em>. A Green Line divides, for ten points, what European island country with capital at Nicosia?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Cyprus</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This city was restored by Decriannus on the orders of Hadrian, after it was destroyed by Lukuas during the Kitos War. This city was later the site of an infamous massacre of all its male inhabitants after they had directed insulting satires at Caracalla. During a dispute between this city\u2019s governor Orestes and its bishop Cyril, the mathematician Hypatia was killed here by a Christian mob. This city\u2019s Musaeum [\u201dmuseum\u201d] housed an institution allegedly burned by Julius Caesar, causing a great loss of ancient texts. For ten points, name this ancient Egyptian city, famed for its lighthouse and library.", "answer": "<b> Alexandria</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Harry Truman once claimed that this man would \u201cgive his right eye to take over\u201d the US. After the Apalachin Meeting, this man created the \u201cTop Hoodlum Program\u201d to target members of the Mafia. Fred Hampton of the Black Panther Party was killed by this man\u2019s organization as part of the COINTELPRO program. This man\u2019s prot\u00b4eg\u00b4e, Clyde Tolson, succeeded him in 1972 and may have been his lover. For ten points, name this director of the FBI from 1935 to 1972.", "answer": "J. Edgar<b> Hoover</b> (accept John Edgar<b> Hoover</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One of these people named Jean Calas was posthumously exonerated by Louis XV from charges of murdering his son. These people were forced to house ill-behaved soldiers with permission to abuse their hosts in a policy called<em> dragonnades</em> [drah-goh-nahd]. The Edict of Potsdam encouraged the relocation of these people to Prussia, and the Duke of Buckingham attempted to help these people at the Siege of La Rochelle. For ten points, name these people, members of the French Reformed Church who were once protected by the Edict of Nantes [nahnt].", "answer": "<b> Huguenots</b> (accept<b> French Protestants</b>; accept<b> French Calvinists</b> until \u201cFrench Reformed Church\u201d is read; prompt on partial answers accordingly)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This material makes up a Paleolithic sculpture of a woman\u2019s head found in 1892 and called the Venus of Brassempuoy. The Lewis chessmen, discovered in Scotland in 1831, were carved from this material. Along with gold and wood, this material was used to create Phidias\u2019 statues of both Zeus at Olympia and the Athena Parthenos. For ten points, name this material used in chryselephantine sculpture, derived from the teeth of animals, often elephants.", "answer": "<b> ivory</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This politician declared \u201cthere is a higher law than the Constitution\u201d in opposition to the Compromise of 1850. This Cabinet member\u2019s work with foreign minister Eduard de Stoeckl allowed a foreign government to pay back a loan from the Rothschilds. This man, who was nearly killed by Lewis Powell the same night Lincoln was assassinated, spent $7.2 million on an \u201cIcebox\u201d purchased from Russia. For ten points, name this Secretary of State whose \u201cFolly\u201d was the purchase of Alaska.", "answer": "William<b> Seward</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city, once known as New Arkhangelsk, was the capital of Alaska Territory prior to Juneau.", "answer": "<b> Sitka</b> Page 5", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One country failed to halt the Greater Wrath during this war when it lost the Battle of Gangut. One leader during this war was killed at the Siege of Fredriksten, after he convinced one country to conduct the Pruth River Campaign. The Surrender at Perevolochna destroyed one side\u2019s army of Caroleans during this war after Adam Leuwenhaupt lost the Battle of Poltava. The Treaty of Nystad ended, for ten points, what war in which Sweden\u2019s Charles XII was defeated by Peter the Great of Russia?", "answer": "<b> Great Northern</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "These people denounced others as \u201cclinging vines\u201d in the first issue of a magazine named for them. Dorothy Bromley described these people as \u201ctruly modern,\u201d and Max Fleischer created a cartoon version of this type of person that Hays Code regulators eventually altered. F. Scott Fitzgerald wrote a collection of short stories titled for these people and \u201cphilosophers.\u201d Followers of this style, a descendant of the Gibson Girl, often engaged in \u201cpetting parties,\u201d bobbed their hair, and resisted Prohibition. For ten points, name this generation of young women in the Roaring Twenties.", "answer": "<b> flapper</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One king of this name was praised by Odo of Deuil in his chronicle of the Second Crusade. Two decades before he actually took the throne, another king of this name tried to overthrow his father in a revolt called the Praguerie [\u201dPrague\u201d-er-ee]; that king of this</b> <b>name manipulated his (+)</b> <b>vassals to centralize power, earning him the nickname \u201cThe</b> <b>vassals to centralize power, earning him the nickname \u201cThe</b> <b>Universal Spider.\u201d Another king of this name died near Carthage while on the (*)</b> <b>Universal Spider.\u201d Another king of this name died near Carthage while on the (*)</b> Eighth Crusade, which he had called after his failure in the Seventh. For ten points, give this name of multiple French kings, the ninth of whom was canonized for his crusading.", "answer": "<b> Louis</b> (accept<b> Louis</b> the 7th, 11th, and/or 9th)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>John Quincy Adams wrote that two presidents were \u201cfor twelve years the tool\u201d of one holder of this position. A member of the Kitchen Cabinet who held this position founded</b> <b>Gallaudet University for the Deaf; that man was (+)</b> <b>Amos Kendall. Thomas J. Brady</b> <b>served under a holder of this position when he became embroiled in a Grant administration scandal involving the corrupt sale of \u201cstar (*)</b> routes.\u201d Samuel Osgood was the first Constitutional holder of, for ten points, what position that lost Cabinet status in 1971, was officially first held by Ben Franklin, and oversees the delivery of mail?", "answer": "United States<b> Postmaster General</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This event was called \u201ca curtain raiser to the sordid drama of Globalisation\u201d by Satinath Sarangi, an activist for its victims. A film subtitled \u201cA Prayer in the Rain\u201d chronicles this event through the lens of everyday people, including a rickshaw driver. A photograph of</b> <b>this event\u2019s aftermath shows a hand above the face of a (+)</b> <b>glassy-eyed girl buried in</b> <b>debris. CEO Warren Anderson was charged for his role in this event, which took place in (*) </b> Madhya Pradesh. Pulmonary edema was a major cause of death in this event, which occurred at a Union Carbide facility. Thousands of people died in, for ten points, what 1984 gas leak in India?", "answer": "<b> Bhopal</b> disaster (accept descriptions of the<b> Bhopal</b> gas tragedy; prompt on descriptive answers that don\u2019t say Bhopal) Page 10", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>The first section of this work uses a \u201cB flat, E flat, D, B flat\u201d motif to represent a ruined castle, and another quotes \u201cYe Who Are Warriors of God.\u201d The second piece in this work</b> <b>quotes \u201cLa Mantovana\u201d and opens with a pair of (+)</b> <b>flutes representing the \u201cCold\u201d and</b> <b>\u201cWarm\u201d branches of the title river. This work depicts Vy\u02c7sehrad [vee-SHARE-rahd], the Hussite stronghold of Tabor, as well as a (*)</b> river that flows through Prague. For ten points, name this set of six patriotic symphonic poems, including \u201cThe Moldau,\u201d by Czech composer Bedrich Smetana.", "answer": "<b> M\u00b4a Vlast</b> (or<b> My Homeland</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This author attacked \u201cvain gospellers\u201d and \u201cpapal riffraff\u201d in her book</b><em><b> The Lamentations </b><b>of a Sinner</b></em><b>, whose release made her the first English woman to publish under her own name. This woman\u2019s first marriage was to a trustee of Thomas Kiddell named (+) Edward Burgh. In her most famous role, she reconciled with a king by claiming that she argued with him only to help take his mind off his sore leg. This woman was allowed to keep the (*)</b> title of \u201cqueen dowager\u201d until her death, unlike earlier figures like Catherine of Aragon. For ten points, name this sixth and final wife of Henry VIII.", "answer": "Catherine<b> Parr</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man was allegedly murdered by Mansfield Cumming\u2019s British agents. This man\u2019s lifestyle was the subject of the \u201cstaircase notes,\u201d and controversy arose over his membership in the hedonistic (+) Khlysty sect. He survived a stabbing from Khionia Guseva, an agent of the priest Iliodor. After this enemy of Felix Yusupov grew in power thanks to his ability to stop the (*)</b> bleeding of the hemophiliac Alexei, this man was poisoned, shot four times, clubbed, and drowned in the Neva River. For ten points, name this Russian mystic, a friend of the family of Nicholas II.", "answer": "Grigory Yefimovich<b> Rasputin</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The central group of this novel is twice insulted by being compared to \u201cmule drivers\u201dand \u201cmud diggers.\u201d The main character of this novel is disappointed when a friend asks him to return a yellow (+) envelope that he had been given in case the friend died. This novel, in which (*)</b> Wilson is repeatedly referred to as \u201cThe Loud Soldier,\u201d ends after a member of the 304th Regiment picks up a flag that had been dropped by a dead standard bearer. For ten points, name this Civil War novel written by Stephen Crane.", "answer": "The<b> Red Badge of Courage</b> Page 11", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>In 1974, this law\u2019s requirements were found to include bilingual alternatives in</b><em><b> Torres </b><b>v. Sachs</b></em><b>, a case financed by the Puerto Rican Legal Defense Fund. After 1982, the second article of this law increasingly became the subject of litigation after the creation of its</b> <b>\u201cresults test.\u201d (+)</b> <b>Section 5 of this law created a requirement of federal pre-clearance in</b> <b>jurisdictions with prior histories of discrimination; that requirement was effectively ended by the 2013 case (*) </b> <em>Shelby County v. Holder</em>. For ten points, name this 1965 law that sought to enforce the 15th Amendment by ending literacy tests and other obstacles meant to keep minorities from participating in elections.", "answer": "<b> Voting Rights</b> Act of 1965 ", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This kingdom\u2019s James I published an early book on maritime law and was forced to give up his northern claims after the Treaty of Corbeil. A crusade against this</b> <b>kingdom was ended by the Treaty of (+)</b> <b>Tarascon. This kingdom opposed the</b> <b>Albigensian Crusade targeting its neighbor to the north, Toulouse. This kingdom annexed (*) </b> Sicily after the War of the Sicilian Vespers and came to dominate the western Mediterranean. For ten points, name this kingdom that, after the marriage of Ferdinand and Isabella, joined with Castile.", "answer": "<b> Aragon</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}